# **BANUCHANDAR ESAKKIMUTHU**

(437) 559-6655 – bcesakki@hotmail.com – www.linkedin.com/in/ebanuchandar

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Highly Skilled and Experienced Data Science professional with **over 7 years of experience** across Semiconductor, Tire & Steel Manufacturing, E-Commerce, Fleet Management Industries, Information Technology and Government Agencies. Bringing specialized expertise in **Business Intelligence**, **Analytics**, **Database Design and Insights**. **VISA STATUS**: Canadian Permanent Resident.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Senior Data Analyst, Micron Technology, India

2021 - 2022

- Monitored traceability KPIs from various Package Assembly and Test processes using Snowflake (Data Warehouse), Big
  Query, Hive, Tableau and SQL Servers for NAND, DRAM and Module/SSD products and created Tableau Dashboards
  for early detection of production and data quality issues.
- Acted as a **Subject Matter Expert** in the areas of data analytics & Visualization and system integration.
- Developed and designed visual dashboards in **Power BI** to track projects, work hours and various other project metrics.
- Managed System integration and Data Project which enables data monitoring of **assembly memory products** yield and traceability parameters in the **O/S Test** process.
- Responsible for Projects involving changes and standardizing of **Tooling, Direct & Indirect Materials and Processes** (**Assembly & Test Processes**) across various internal and external sites in Asia.
- Responsible for continuous improvements and execution of strategic roadmap for change management & Global security initiatives.

### Process Engineer, Prodistics LLC, Naperville, Illinois, USA

2016 - 2021

Worked on Projects with various Clients like Illinois Board of Higher Education, Continental Tire, ArcelorMittal, Wheels Inc and Next Level Performance.

- Responsible for **data modeling, architecture design** and **implementation** of Illinois longitudinal data collection system (analytics application) resulted in reduction of file processing time by 70%.
- Developed business process, Created **SQL Server Views, Stored procedures, SQL jobs, ETL** process (extract, transform, and load), and alerts & deployed **Websites, data encryption** and **Services** for new web applications used for institution/course approvals for Illinois Board of Higher Education.
- Analyzed various **Data sets** in SQL Databases to facilitate **root cause analysis** and to draw **data-driven decisions** for complex problems associated with manufacturing, PLC, and IT processes in Continental Tire facilities across the United States.
- Analyzed existing inventory systems, IT infrastructure and databases(SQL Server and Oracle) in ArcelorMittal, Suggested continuous improvements and Implemented inventory applications and databases used for tracking coils in Railcar, shipping & external processors that led to improved productivity(Audit time were reduced by 75% and automated data consolidation saved about 95% man hours), quality(saved 5 Million USD per quarter on coil quality claims shipped via rail), and less labor (50% reduction in manual labor for coil inventory)
- Analyzed data using SQL Server, Azure app insights, and storage to determine data discrepancies.

# Industrial Engineer, Genesee Stamping and Fabrication Inc, Grand Prairie, Texas, USA

2014 - 2015

Developed Routers and BOM for new parts using Globalshop solution (ERP system).

#### **EDUCATION**

Master of Science in Industrial Engineering, The University of Texas at Arlington, USA

Bachelor of Technology in Electronics and Communication Engineering, Amrita Vishwa Vidyapeetham University

2012

# **CERTIFICATION**

IBM Data Science Professional Certificate

Six Sigma Green Belt Certification, Institute of Industrial Engineers

2020

**SOFTWARE SKILLS:** Snowflake, SQL Server, Power BI, Tableau, Google Cloud Platform BigQuery, Power Automate, Python, JQL, Jira, Confluence, Azure DevOps Server, Visual Studio, Visual Code, SolidWorks, AutoCAD, C#, HTML, IIS, UXPin, Angular, Azure, AWS, GitHub, Assembla, Bitbucket, IBM Cloud, Minitab, MATLAB, SSIS, MySQL, Oracle Developer, Hive, Team Center.